PROFESSOR: OK.
Let's think about how we're going to
deal with games like chess, where we
can't possibly search
the whole game tree.
Essentially we've got
resource limits--
in this case, time--
that tell us we can only look forward
so far into the tree before the
exponential growth of
the tree gets us.
This is always going to be the
case in a realistic game.
You will not be able to
search to the leaf.
So you've got this tree
like the one shown.
There's alternating min and max layers,
and way down at the bottom
somewhere are the actual terminal
utilities, which may all be plus and
minus 1, but we can't
search down to them.
So the solution--
pretty straightforward.
We're going to do a depth-limited
search.
We're only going to actually go down
as far as we have time for.
So we're going to search for some
limited depth in the tree.
Now the problem is, when we get to the
end of our search, we don't have
terminal utilities, because we're not
actually at the end of the game.
We're just a few moves ahead.
So what we need is we need to replace
the terminal utilities in the min and
max algorithm with what's called an
evaluation function, which takes a
non-terminal position and gives us some
estimate of what the terminal
utility under that tree would
be under min and max flat.
So for example, we might cut
the tree off right here and
stick in these numbers.
Are these the min and max values?
Almost certainly not, but
they're something.
So now we do our search, we run min and
max, and we propagate everything
up to the root.
This is not the min and
max value at the root.
This is the min and max value under the
assumption that this evaluation
function accurately represents the min
and max values of the truncated notes.
As an example here, back to chess, if
we've got about 100 seconds to move,
and we can explore 10,000 nodes per
second, which actually isn't very
many, that means we can
check something like a
million nodes per move.
And with alpha beta pruning that we're
going to talk about later, that means
you'll get to something like depth 8,
and that will not be a world champion
chess player, but it will be decent.
So this kind of idea of truncation
is very important.
We're going to have to truncate, so
we'll want to do it as well as
possible, meaning go as deeply as we
can and plug in as good numbers as
possible for the evaluation function.
Of course our guarantee of optimal play
is gone, because these are no
longer the min and max values.
Our valuation function may not be very
good at knowing that there's a trap
just beyond the horizon.
Searching more plies, that is, going
deeper into this tree, makes a big
difference.
And we'll see examples
of that in a second.
One cool thing you can do is you can
do iterative deepening here.
What that means is you do a search for
one move in response, one ply, and
then two, and then three,
and then four.
At some point, you'll run out of time.
At any given time, you've done
essentially the best search you can
do, and you always have a move.
And the more time you get, the
better that move gets.
That's what's called an anytime
algorithm, and it's a really nice
property to have.
You've always got an answer, and that
answer gets better over time.
So depth matters.
Evaluation functions are
going to be imperfect.
We're going to talk about how we can
make them as good as possible, but
they're always going to be imperfect.
However, the deeper you bury them into
a tree, the less their imperfection
matters in general.
So we want to make them as good as
possible, but we also want to bury
them deep in the tree.
In general, the deeper you search, the
more likely you are to see what's
actually going on.
So here you have the agent on
the top who's got a very
hazy view of the future.
Maybe the future looks quite scary.
A monster mountain.
But then you look just a little bit
further, and you realize, it's just
some nice trees.
And it's always better to look further,
but you'll always have a
limit to your resources.
This is actually an important example
of a trade-off here between the
complexity of the features that go
into the evaluation function--
you could make a really complicated
evaluation function, and then you
wouldn't have to search so deeply to
behave well, or you could have a very
simple evaluation function, and you
could compensate by doing more min and
max search.
And there's this trade-off between
whether your behavior arises from the
computation or from the complexity
of your stored evaluation.
Let's take a look at this in practice.
So here's a configuration.
Let's think about this for a second.
We'd like to eat that dot, and if we
look forward just a couple steps, we
won't be able to see the actual eating
of the dot, or any future collisions
with the ghosts.
We're just going to look forward and see
whether or not we can be closer or
farther from the dot, but we'll have
to have an evaluation function that
says, being close to the dot is better
than being farther, or it's all going
to look the same to the
evaluation function.
So let's see what happens when
we search two ahead.
Well, we're going to move towards
the dot, unsurprisingly.
Except now what happens?
We get pinned.
What happens if instead, we have a
mastermind Pac Man here, and we can
see all the way into the future?
We can see the whole game play out,
which on this board is feasible?
Well, now what should we do?
The critical thing is that blue ghost is
going to go somewhere, and once it
goes somewhere, it's committed.
So what we should actually do--
and this is not obvious
from a horizon of 2--
is move towards the orange ghost,
because we're still not actually in
any danger.
A reasonable evaluation function that
looks just a little bit in the future
would say, that's crazy.
You move towards the ghost
and away from the dot.
But in fact, if you look deeply enough
into the tree, you see that what this
allows you to do is force the blue ghost
to make a decision before you
have to, and that lets you get around.
And that is Mastermind Pac Man.